This is the Natural History Museum in Rotterdam,
هذا هو متحف التاريخ الطبيعي بروتردام،
where I work as a curator.
حيث أعمل أمينا.
It's my job to make sure the collection stays okay,
عملي هو التّأكد أنّ المجموعة تبقى على ما يرام،
and that it grows,
وأنّها تكبر،
and basically it means I collect dead animals.
وهذا يعني أنّني أقوم بجمع الحيوانات الميّتة.
Back in 1995,
سابقا، سنة 1995،
we got a new wing next to the museum.
بنينا جناحا جديدا جانب المتحف.
It was made of glass,
كان مصنوعا من الزّجاج،
and this building really helped me to do my job good.
وهذا المبنى ساعدني فعلا على القيام بعملي.
The building was a true bird-killer.
هذا المبنى كان قاتل طيور حقيقيّا.
You may know that birds don't understand
تعلمون أنّ الطّيور لا تفهم
the concept of glass. They don't see it,
ما معنى "زجاج". لا تستطيع رؤيته،
so they fly into the windows and get killed.
لذلك، تصطدم بالنّوافذ و تموت.
The only thing I had to do was go out,
كلّ ما كان عليّ فعله هو الخروج،
pick them up, and have them stuffed for the collection.
جمع جثثها، ثمّ حشوها لإضافتها للمجموعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And in those days,
في تلك الأيّام،
I developed an ear to identify birds
طوّرت قدرة سمع تميّز الطّيور،
just by the sound of the bangs they made against the glass.
فقط من خلال أصوات اصطدامها على الزّجاج.
And it was on June 5, 1995,
في الخامس من يونيو 1995،
that I heard a loud bang against the glass
سمعت صوت اصطدام على الزّجاج
that changed my life and ended that of a duck.
غيّر حياتي و أنهى حياة بطّة.
And this is what I saw when I looked out of the window.
وهذا كان ما رأيته عندما نظرت خارج النّافذة.
This is the dead duck. It flew against the window.
هذا هو البطّ الميّت. لقد طار نحو النّافذة.
It's laying dead on its belly.
ارتمى ميّتا على بطنه.
But next to the dead duck is a live duck,
لكن حذو البطّ الميّت، كان هناك بطّ حيّ،
and please pay attention.
و من فضلكم أن تنتبهوا.
Both are of the male sex.
كلاهما كانا ذكرين.
And then this happened.
ثمّ إليكم ما حدث.
The live duck mounted the dead duck,
البطّ الحيّ صعد فوق الميّت،
and started to copulate.
و بدأ في التزاوج معه.
Well, I'm a biologist. I'm an ornithologist.
حسنا، أنا بيولوجيّ. أنا عالم طيور.
I said, "Something's wrong here."
قلت في نفسي:"هناك أمر ليس على ما يرام".
One is dead, one is alive. That must be necrophilia.
أحدهما ميّت و الآخر حيّ، إنّها مضاجعة الموتى.
I look. Both are of the male sex.
نظرت. كلاهما كانا ذكرين.
Homosexual necrophilia.
مضاجعة موتى مثليّة.
So I -- (Laughter)
لذلك -- (ضحك)
I took my camera, I took my notebook,
أخذت آلة التصوير خاصّتي، و دفتري،
took a chair, and started to observe this behavior.
وأخذت كرسيّا، و شرعت في مراقبة هذا السّلوك.
After 75 minutes — (Laughter) —
بعد 75 دقيقة، -- (ضحك) --
I had seen enough, and I got hungry,
كنت قد شاهدت بما فيه الكفاية، و شعرت بالجوع،
and I wanted to go home.
وأردت الذهاب إلى المنزل.
So I went out, collected the duck,
لذلك خرجت، أخذت البطّ،
and before I put it in the freezer,
وقبل وضعه في الثّلاجة،
I checked if the victim was indeed of the male sex.
تأكّدت إن كان بالفعل من جنس الذّكر.
And here's a rare picture of a duck's penis,
وهذه صورة نادرة لقضيب البطّ،
so it was indeed of the male sex.
إذا فهو بالفعل ذكر.
It's a rare picture because there are 10,000 species of birds
لقد كانت صورة نادرة، لأنّ هناك 10.000 نوعا من الطّيور
and only 300 possess a penis.
و300 منها فقط تمتلك قضيبا.
[The first case of homosexual necrophilia in the mallard Anas platyrhynchos (Aves:Anatidae)]
[أوّل حالة جماع موتى مثليّ في البطّ البرّي]
I knew I'd seen something special,
علمت أنّني شاهدت أمرا مميّزا،
but it took me six years to decide to publish it.
لكن الأمر استغرقني 6 سنوات قد أن أقرّر نشره.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, it's a nice topic for a birthday party
ستكون قصّة ممتعة في حفل عيد ميلاد،
or at the coffee machine,
أو في آلة بيع القهوة،
but to share this among your peers is something different.
لكن مشاركتها مع رفاقك هو أمر مختلف.
I didn't have the framework.
لم يكن لديّ الإطار المناسب.
So after six years, my friends and colleagues urged me to publish,
لذلك و بعد 6 سنوات، حثّني زملائي وأصدقائي على النّشر،
so I published "The first case of homosexual necrophilia
لذلك نشرت "أوّل حالة جماع موتى مثليّ
in the mallard."
عند البطّ البرّي".
And here's the situation again.
إليكم الموقف مجدّدا.
A is my office,
A هو مكتبي.
B is the place where the duck hit the glass,
B هو مكان اصطدام البطّ بالزّجاج،
and C is from where I watched it.
و C هو مكان رؤيتي للأمر.
And here are the ducks again.
وها هو البطّ مجدّدا.
As you probably know, in science,
كما تعلمون على الأرجح، في العلم،
when you write a kind of special paper,
عندما تكتب نوعا من المقالات الخاصّة،
only six or seven people read it.
فقط 6 أو 7 أناس يقرؤونه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But then something good happened.
لكن شيء جيّد حصل فيما بعد.
I got a phone call from a person called Marc Abrahams,
تلقّيت مكالمة هاتفيّة من شخص يدعى مارك أبراهامز،
and he told me, "You've won a prize with your duck paper:
وقال لي:"لقد ربحت جائزة عن مقال البطّ الذي كتبته:
the Ig Nobel Prize."
جائزة نوبل للحماقة."
And the Ig Nobel Prize —
وجائزة نوبل للحماقة --
(Laughter) (Applause) —
(ضحك) (تصفيق) --
the Ig Nobel Prize honors research
جائزة نوبل للحماقة تعطى للبحوث
that first makes people laugh, and then makes them think,
التي تجعل النّاس يضحكون، ثمّ تجعلهم يفكّرون،
with the ultimate goal to make more people
بهدف جعل أكثر عدد من النّاس
interested in science.
مهتمّة بالعلوم.
That's a good thing, so I accepted the prize.
هذا أمر إيجابيّ، لذلك قبلت بالجائزة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I went -- let me remind you that Marc Abrahams
ذهبت -- دعوني أذكّركم أنّ مارك أبراهامز
didn't call me from Stockholm.
لم يتّصل بي من ستوكهولم.
He called me from Cambridge, Massachusetts.
بل من كامبردج، ولاية ماساتشوستس.
So I traveled to Boston, to Cambridge,
لذلك سافرت إلى بوسطن، إلى كامبردج،
and I went to this wonderful Ig Nobel Prize ceremony
وحضرت احتفال جائزة نوبل للحماقة رائعا
held at Harvard University, and this ceremony
الذي أقيم بجامعة هارفرد، وهذه الجائزة
is a very nice experience.
لقد كانت تجربة رائعة.
Real Nobel laureates hand you the prize.
الحائزون على جوائز نوبل الحقيقيّة يسلّمونك الجائزة.
That's the first thing.
هذا الأمر الأوّل.
And there are nine other winners who get prizes.
وكان هناك 9 آخرون نالوا الجائزة.
Here's one of my fellow winners. That's Charles Paxton
هذا أحد الذين ربحوا. يدعى شارلز باكسون
who won the 2000 biology prize for his paper,
الذي ربح جائزة البيولوجيا لسنة 2000 لمقاله،
"Courtship behavior of ostriches towards humans
"السّلوك الودود للنّعام تجاه البشر
under farming conditions in Britain."
في بيئة فلاحيّة ببريطانيا."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I think there are one or two more
وأظنّ أنّ هناك فرد أو اثنين في هذه الغرفة
Ig Nobel Prize winners in this room.
من الفائزين بجائزة نوبل للحماقة.
Dan, where are you? Dan Ariely?
دان، أين أنت؟ دان أريلي؟
Applause for Dan.
صفّقوا لدان.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Dan won his prize in medicine
دان فاز بجائزته في ميدان الطّب
for demonstrating that high-priced fake medicine
لتبيينه أنّ الأدوية المزيّفة الغالية الثّمن
works better than low-priced fake medicine.
تعمل أفضل من الأدوية المزيّفة الرّخيصة الثّمن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So here's my one minute of fame,
إذن هذا هو وقت اشتهاري،
my acceptance speech,
خطاب تلقيّ الجائزة،
and here's the duck.
وهذا هو البطّ.
This is its first time on the U.S. West Coast.
إنّها المرّة الأولى له في السّاحل الغربي الأمريكيّ.
I'm going to pass it around.
سأقوم بتمريره.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah?
حسنا؟
You can pass it around.
يمكنكم تمريره.
Please note it's a museum specimen,
أرغب أن أنوّه إلى أنّه نموذج من المتحف،
but there's no chance you'll get the avian flu.
لكن لن يعرّضك للإصابة بانفلونزا الطيور.
After winning this prize, my life changed.
بعد الفوز بتلك الجائزة، تغيّرت حياتي.
In the first place, people started to send me
أولا، بدأ النّاس يراسلونني
all kinds of duck-related things,
حول كلّ ما يرتبط بالبطّ،
and I got a real nice collection.
وأصبحت لديّ مجموعة رائعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
More importantly,
لكن الأهمّ،
people started to send me their observations
هو أنّ النّاس بدؤوا يراسلونني ملاحظاتهم
of remarkable animal behavior,
حول سلوكات حيوانيّة ملفتة للنّظر،
and believe me, if there's an animal misbehaving on this planet,
وصدّقوني، إن كان هناك سلوكات سيّئة للحيوانات على هذا الكوكب،
I know about it.
فأنا على دراية بها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is a moose.
هذا موظ.
It's a moose trying to copulate
موظ يحاول التّزاوج
with a bronze statue of a bison.
مع تمثال نحاسيّ لثور أمريكيّ.
This is in Montana, 2008.
هذه موناتنا، سنة 2008.
This is a frog that tries to copulate with a goldfish.
هذا ضفدع يحاول التّزاوج مع سمكة ذهبيّة.
This is the Netherlands, 2011.
هذه هولندا سنة 2011.
These are cane toads in Australia.
هناك ضفادع القصب بأستراليا.
This is roadkill.
هذا حادث اصطدام.
Please note that this is necrophilia.
هذه حالة جماع موتى.
It's remarkable: the position.
الوضعيّة مثيرة للاهتمام.
The missionary position is very rare in the animal kingdom.
هذه الوضعيّة الجنسيّة نادرة جدّا في مملكة الحيوان.
These are pigeons in Rotterdam.
هذا حمام بروتردام.
Barn swallows in Hong Kong, 2004.
وهذه طيور خطّاف بهونغ كونغ سنة 2004.
This is a turkey in Wisconsin
هذا ديك روميّ في ويسكنسن
on the premises of the Ethan Allen juvenile correctional institution.
في مقرّ إصلاحيّة إيثان ألين.
It took all day,
استغرقني الأمر يوما كاملا،
and the prisoners had a great time.
و المساجين قضوا وقتا ممتعا.
So what does this mean?
إذن ماذا يعني كلّ هذا؟
I mean, the question I ask myself,
السّؤال الذي أطرحه على نفسي هو،
why does this happen in nature?
لماذا يحدث كلّ هذا في الطبيعة؟
Well, what I concluded
حسنا، لقد استنتجت
from reviewing all these cases
من خلال مراقبة كلّ هذه الحالات
is that it is important that this happens
هو أنّ هذا يحدث
only when death is instant
فقط عندما يكون هناك موت سريع
and in a dramatic way
وبطريقة تراجيديّة
and in the right position for copulation.
وفي الوضعيّة المناسبة للجماع.
At least, I thought it was till I got these slides.
على الأقلّ، ظننت أنّ الأمر كذلك إلى أن حصلت على هذه الشّرائح.
And here you see a dead duck.
وهنا ترون بطّا ميّتا.
It's been there for three days,
كان هناك لأيّام،
and it's laying on its back.
ملقيّا على ظهره.
So there goes my theory of necrophilia.
تلك هي نظريّتي عن جماع الموتى.
Another example of the impact
مثال آخر عن تأثير
of glass buildings on the life of birds.
المباني الزّجاجية في حياة الطيور.
This is Mad Max, a blackbird who lives in Rotterdam.
هذا ماد ماكس، وهو شحرور يعيش بروتردام.
The only thing this bird did was fly against this window
الأمر الوحيد الذي كان يقوم به هو الطيران نحو هذه النّافذة
from 2004 to 2008, day in and day out.
من 2004 إلى 2008،
Here he goes, and here's a short video.
هاهو ذا، إليكم هذا الفيديو القصير.
(Music) (Clunk)
(موسيقى) (كلانك)
(Clunk)
(كلانك)
So what this bird does
ما يفعله هذ ا الطائر
is fight his own image.
هو محاربته صورته.
He sees an intruder in his territory,
إنّه يرى دخيلا بمنطقته،
and it's coming all the time and he's there,
وهو هناك طيلة الوقت
so there is no end to it.
لذلك ما من نهاية لهذا.
And I thought, in the beginning -- I studied this bird for a couple of years --
ظننت في البداية -- قمت بدراسة هذا الطائر لسنوات --
that, well, shouldn't the brain of this bird be damaged?
ألا يفترض بدماغه أن يكون قد تضرّر؟
It's not. I show you here some slides,
لا، لم يتضرّر. سأريكم صورا،
some frames from the video,
وبعض اللّقطات من هذا الفيديو،
and at the last moment before he hits the glass,
وفي اللحظة الأخيرة السابقة لاصطدامه بالزجاج،
he puts his feet in front,
يضع رجله أمامه،
and then he bangs against the glass.
ثمّ يضرب الزجاج.
So I'll conclude to invite you all to Dead Duck Day.
إذن سأختم بدعوتكم جميعا إلى يوم البطّ الميّت.
That's on June 5 every year.
إنّه في الخامس من يونيو كلّ سنة.
At five minutes to six in the afternoon,
قبل السّادسة مساء،
we come together at the Natural History Museum in Rotterdam,
نتقابل كلّنا في متحف التّاريخ الطبيعيّ بروتردام،
the duck comes out of the museum,
البطّ يخرج من المتحف،
and we try to discuss new ways
ونحاول نقاش طرق جديدة
to prevent birds from colliding with windows.
لمنع الطيور من الاصطدام بالنّوافذ.
And as you know, or as you may not know,
قد تعلمون، أو قد لا تعلمون،
this is one of the major causes of death
أنّ ذلك هو سبب الموت الأولّ
for birds in the world.
للطيور في العالم.
In the U.S. alone, a billion birds die
في الولايات المتحدة وحدها، يموت مليار طائر
in collision with glass buildings.
نتيجة الاصطدام بأبنية زجاجيّة.
And when it's over, we go to a Chinese restaurant
ثمّ نذهب إلى مطعم صينيّ
and we have a six-course duck dinner.
ونشتري عشاء بطّ.
So I hope to see you
أتمنّى أن أراكم
next year in Rotterdam, the Netherlands,
السنة المقبلة في روتردام، بهولندا،
for Dead Duck Day.
في يوم البطّ الميّت.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Oh, sorry.
أوه، عفوا.
May I have my duck back, please?
هل يمكنني استعادة بطّتي، لو سمحتم؟
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.